<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<feed xmlns="http://www.w3.org/2005/Atom">

  <title>The Way</title>
  <generator uri="https://github.com/jekyll/jekyll">Jekyll v3.6.2</generator>
    <icon>http://hr2rh.com/apple-touch-icon-precomposed.png</icon>
  <subtitle>The Way of Resourceful Humans is the most thoughtful framework to kill Complexity and Complicatedness in your Enterprise. Turn Peer Feedback and entrepreneurial work of Human Resources into Resourceful Humans. Simple. Social. Realtime. Use our work (self-) managemanent tools like staRHs, netwoRHk and caRHds.
</subtitle>
  <link href="http://hr2rh.com/atom.xml" rel="self"/>
  <link href="http://hr2rh.com/" rel="alternate" type="text/html"/>
  <updated>2017-11-26T07:11:03+00:00</updated>
  <id>http://hr2rh.com/</id>
  <author>
    <name>Resourceful Humans</name>
    <uri>http://hr2rh.com/</uri>
    <email>info@resourceful-humans.com</email>
  </author>

  
  <entry>
    <title>DEMOKRATIE. WOLLEN. KÖNNEN. DÜRFEN.</title>
    <link href="http://hr2rh.com/demokratie-wollen-koennen-duerfen"/>
    <updated>2015-05-05T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://hr2rh.com/demokratie-wollen-koennen-duerfen</id>
    <author>
      <name>Resourceful Humans</name>
      <uri>http://hr2rh.com/</uri>
      <email>info@resourceful-humans.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      
      &lt;p&gt;Ein Märchen wurde wahr im Sommer 2014! Der erste europäische Weltmeister auf südamerikanischem Boden – Deutschland besiegt Argentinien mit 1:0. Ein Dokumentarfilm zu Ehren dieses außergewöhnlichen Ereignisses wurde kürzlich veröffentlicht. Sein Name? Die Mannschaft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Kürzlich wurde der Goldene Ball an den besten Fußballer der Welt verliehen. Die Wahl fällt auf den Ausnahmeathleten Ronaldo. Oft wird das Prinzip des Sports für Führung strapaziert. Doch auf welchem Prinzip basiert unsere vorherrschende Managementlogik? Dem der Mannschaft, oder der des Ausnahmetalents?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In den meisten Fällen gleicht Performancemanagement der Wahl des Goldenen Balls. Belohnung von individueller Klasse. Oder Grad der Zielerreichung des HR’lers? Paradoxerweise ist “Teamarbeit” oft eine Komponente der individuellen Leistungsbeurteilung. Teams sind in dieser Denke bestenfalls ausführende Elemente. Sicherlich keine Partner.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Oliver Kahn beschrieb im Interview die kollektive Entwicklung des Deutschen Nationalteams mit klaren Worten: Ein Trainer, der aus dem Ausscheiden in der letzten WM gegen Italien seine Lektion zog. Ein Team, welches kein Spiel um Platz 3 mehr wollte. Fortan traf Löw Entscheidungen demokratisch mit seiner Mannschaft. Diese akzeptierte und begrüßte die Mitverantwortung. Führte Analysen mit dem Trainer gemeinsam durch. Im geteilten Verständnis, dass der Trainer Verantwortung nicht auf sie abwälzte. Denn nach außen verteidigte er kontroverse Entscheidungen wie die Position Philipp Lahms als die seinen. Nein, stattdessen führte er seine Mannschaft mit klarem Rahmen (demokratische Mitverantwortung), klarer Erwartung (voller Einsatz für das gemeinsame Ziel) und hielt den Druck weitestmöglich von ihnen fern, damit sie ihr Ziel erreichen würden: Kein Spiel mehr um Platz 3!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;mehr-unternehmens--demokratie-wagen&quot;&gt;Mehr (Unternehmens-) Demokratie wagen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Beispiele dieser Art Führung im betriebswirtschaftlichen Kontext gibt es mittlerweile genug und ihre Zahl steigt. Erfolgreiche wie SEMCO, W.L. Gore, Morningstar und AES. Gescheiterte wie Crytek und das alte HP. Junge wilde wie Valve, VAGAS, Haufe und Zappos. Sie alle verbindet Demokratie als selbst-organisierendes Führungsbetriebssystem von, für und durch mündige Erwachsene und ein gemeinschaftliches, sinnhaftes Ziel.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Doch wie kommt man im unternehmerischen Rahmen von einem diktatorischen Louis van Gaal Trainerstil und einem Verbund höchst-talentierter Individualisten zu einem Löw(en)-Packet?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Zuerst muss verstanden werden, dass Deutschland verlieren musste bevor es zu seiner Größe fand. SEMCO musste fast bankrott, ihr CEO dem Herzinfarkt nahe sein. In allen Beispielen gab es unternehmerische Motivationen ein neues, besseres System zu wählen. Die Profitmaximierung als Triebfeder reicht nicht. Schließlich wollte ja auch jedes Team die WM gewinnen. Kopieren reichte nicht, denn Spanien, die erfolgreichste Mannschaft der letzten Jahrzehnte war bereits ein Auslaufmodel. Es galt die Zukunft zu gestalten. Doch wie?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;die-3-fragezeichen&quot;&gt;Die 3 Fragezeichen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Destilliert bedarf es dreierlei: &lt;em&gt;Wollen&lt;/em&gt; – Sinnhafter Antrieb, &lt;em&gt;Können&lt;/em&gt; – Höchstmaß an Fertigkeit und &lt;em&gt;Dürfen&lt;/em&gt; – Autonomie. Gleichermaßen stehen uns drei Dinge im Weg: Angst, mentale Modelle und externe Einflüsse.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eine Geschäftsführung, die mit einer neuen demokratischen Logik der Unternehmensführung an den Start geht, macht sich angreifbar. Joachim Löw wäre nicht mehr Coach der Nationalmannschaft, wäre er mit seinem Ansatz Vizemeister. Doch Demokratie kann nicht alleinig zum Zwecke “des Titelgewinns” genutzt werden. Demokratie bedeutet Bekenntnis und Menschenbild. Tony Hsieh, gestaltete die Kultur von Zappos aus einer inneren Ablehnung traditioneller asiatischer Erziehung. Ricardo Semler wagte mehr Demokratie aus der Überzeugung dem damals noch undemokratischen Brasilien ein erfolgreiches Vorbild sein zu können.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Dies bedeutet Stolpern. Fallen. Bluten. Aufstehen. Alles unter Druck.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Demokratie ist der bestmögliche Rahmen für nachhaltige Gewinnmaximierung. Der Preis ist die Lernkurve, die es notwendigerweise bedarf. Doch es braucht mittel- und langfristigen unternehmerischen Erfolg. Der Wettbewerbsvorteil engagierter, mündiger Mitarbeiter muss sich zur Validierung des Ansatzes herauskristallisieren. Dies erst schafft Freiräume zum Experimentieren und Skalieren.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;einen-klaren-rahmen-schaffen&quot;&gt;Einen klaren Rahmen schaffen&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wie organisiert man nun praktisch eine solche demokratische Organisation? Im Fußball ist es einfach. Nach 90 oder 120 Minuten verlässt eine Mannschaft als Sieger oder Verlierer den Platz. Erinnern wir uns zurück an die Mannschaft: Klarer Rahmen (demokratische Mitverantwortung), klare Erwartung (voller Einsatz für das gemeinsame Ziel).&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Der Rahmen braucht ein episches Ziel und klare Werte. Wo soll die Reise hingehen und warum?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Der Geschäftsführer kann den Rahmen setzen, doch im Gegensatz zur Anarchie braucht insbesondere Selbst-Organisation klare Regeln, gemeinsame Vokabeln und Disziplin. Hier – beim Einläuten der Demokratie – könnte HR endlich seine neue Rolle finden. Nach der Administrativen Polizeitätigkeit, dem Versagen als Strategischer Partner, bietet die Flucht nach vorne ins Unternehmertum, als Befähiger einer neuen Managementlogik auf Augenhöhe nicht eine sinnhafte Vision der Funktion?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Was hält den HR-Leiter davon ab eine eigene Vision für den Bereich zu definieren? Zum Beispiel als Pionier für unternehmerische Demokratie? Oder nennen wir es menschliches Unternehmertum.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ein aus der Spieleentwicklung abgeleiteter Prozess (moRHale) ermöglicht es, die Kultur eines Teams wie ein Produkt agil zu entwickeln. Anhand drei epischer Fragen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Lieben wir unsere Aufgabe?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Haben wir was wir benötigen unser Bestes zu geben?&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Fühlen wir uns für unseren Beitrag wertgeschätzt?&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;beginnt jedes Team, das für sich passende Umfeld zu gestalten. Dies mag mit scheinbar trivialen Themen wie Lärm oder Temperatur im Großraumbüro beginnen. Doch in dem Maße in dem sich das Team unternehmerisch entwickelt, werden die Themen auch konkreter und unternehmerischer. Zum Beispiel kann das Team einen für sich funktionierenden Recruitment-Prozess schaffen. Vielleicht sollen Bewerber direkt mitarbeiten und dann vom Team demokratisch gewählt werden à la Voice of Germany? Vielleicht will man den Chef wählen? Kann man ohne Probleme von zuhause arbeiten? Alles Fragen, die ans Team zurückgespielt werden.  Am Ende darf es keine Entschuldigungen mehr geben, keine Bestleistung abgerufen zu haben.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;vernetzte-handwerker&quot;&gt;Vernetzte Handwerker&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Nun geht es darum den Rahmen mit Leben zu füllen. Eine Vision muss mit unternehmerischen Zielen beseelt werden (z.B. 10 Million Exemplare des nächsten Produktes absetzen). Validiert wird dieses Ziel beispielhaft durch den (netwoRHk) Prozess. In diesem Prozess definiert ein Leader zuallererst seine Vision. Abgeleitet davon schlägt er konkrete Arbeitspakete vor und verknüpft diese mit Mitarbeitern, welche diese seiner Meinung nach leisten können. Diese Arbeitspakete werden inkl. Zeitschätzung und messbarer Erfolgskriterien als Vorschläge an diese Mitarbeiter versandt. Nun kann jeh’ nach Reifegrad des Teams einiges geschehen:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teams-mit-geringem-unternehmerischen-kompetenzgradwollen--können---dürfen-o&quot;&gt;Teams mit geringem unternehmerischen Kompetenzgrad.&lt;br /&gt;Wollen +, Können -, Dürfen o:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Der Mitarbeiter validiert die Vision mit Zustimmung und übernimmt die Schätzung und Ziele.
Der Mitarbeiter validiert die Vision mit Zustimmung, korrigiert jedoch Schätzung und/oder Ziele.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teams-mit-fortgeschrittenem-unternehmerischen-kompetenzgradwollen--können--dürfen-&quot;&gt;Teams mit fortgeschrittenem unternehmerischen Kompetenzgrad.&lt;br /&gt;Wollen ++, Können +, Dürfen +:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Der Mitarbeiter lehnt das Arbeitspaket ab, schlägt jedoch einen besser geeigneten Kollegen vor.
Der Mitarbeit lehnt die Vision ab indem er das Arbeitspaket ablehnt und macht einen Gegenvorschlag.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h3 id=&quot;teams-mit-kompletten-unternehmerischen-kompetenzgradwollen--können--dürfen-&quot;&gt;Teams mit kompletten unternehmerischen Kompetenzgrad.&lt;br /&gt;Wollen ++, Können ++, Dürfen ++:&lt;/h3&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Die Teammitgliedern begeben sich in einen positiven Ideenwettbewerb um die Vision zu definieren.
Die Teammitglieder definieren neue Arbeitspakete, welche vorher nicht berücksichtigt wurde.
Die Teammitglieder stimmen Arbeitspakete dynamisch mit den Kunden ab.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;So bekommt der Chef nicht nur Transparenz über seine unternehmerisches Standing im Team, sondern auch wie es um die Dimensionen Wollen und Können bestellt ist. Seine Stellschraube ist die Dimension Dürfen. Das Team wird so Schritt für Schritt in die Mitverantwortung genommen. Abstrakte Themen wie “Kultur”, “Personalmarketing”, “Gehaltsabrechnung” und “Recruiting” müssen so gemeinsam in messbare Ziele überführt werden. Die Mitarbeiter handeln so letztlich Verträge mit den Kollegen und Lieferanten direkt aus. Jeder Mitarbeiter ist auch dafür verantwortlich, alles für die eigene Arbeit Nötige selbst zu besorgen. So entsteht ein Unternehmen mit 100% Unternehmertum und 0% Bürokratie, indem alle Teammitglieder selbstbestimmte Beschäftigte sind, die Kommunikation und Koordination mit ihren Kollegen, Kunden, Lieferanten und Branchenkollegen ohne Vorgaben von anderen selbst in die Hand nehmen.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Diese Freiwilligkeit führt zu exponentiell erhöhter Autonomie und Proaktivität im Handeln, besonders in unvorhergesehenen Situationen. Solche Organisationen sind wesentlich agiler, wenn sie auf Probleme treffen als starre Prozessorganisationen. Das Element “mündiger Mitarbeiter”, macht den Unterschied.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;das-geht-doch-gar-nichtoder&quot;&gt;Das geht doch gar nicht…oder?&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Ein Einwand der oft vorgebracht wird, ist, wie das denn bitte mit 10.000 Mitarbeitern funktionieren solle. Dazu zwei Punkte: Wer sich das Spiel der Deutschen Nationalmannschaft genau anschaut, sieht, dass es für den ballbesitzenden Spieler immer ca. 4-5 Anspielstationen gibt. Nicht 10. Im betriebswirtschaftlichen Umfeld arbeiten wir ebenso nie mit mehr als 10-15 Menschen direkt zusammen. Aber durch Transparenz der Teams, kommen ganz neue Ideen, durch ein neues Verständnis des Ganzen und den Wert des eigenen Beitrags im Team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Eines ist sicher. Das Deutsche Team musste oft Stolpern. Fallen. Bluten. Aufstehen. Alles unter Druck. In diesem Beitrag unbehandelt ist eine gigantische Nachwuchsentwicklungsstrategie im Gange, die nach langem Weg in der A-Nationalmannschaft endet. Jedem Unternehmer, der Demokratie wagt, sollte bewusst sein, dass gegenwärtige Ausbildungen dies Geisteshaltung nicht fördern. Demokratisches Unternehmertum erfordert bewusstes Verlernen und Neulernen. Sicher ist aus den Geschichten der Vorreiter – die Investition rechnet sich langfristig. Denn diese Teams spielen fast ohne Manager. Ohne HR. Ohne Trainer.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Schlagen wir nun die Brücke zurück zu Ronaldo: Der Weltfußballer schied mit Portugal in der Vorrunde aus.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Am Ende zählt die Mannschaft.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Und der Titel gibt ihr Recht.&lt;/p&gt;

    </content>
  </entry>
  
  <entry>
    <title>THREE LESSONS HR CAN LEARN FROM MY GRANDMOTHER</title>
    <link href="http://hr2rh.com/three-lessons-hr-can-learn-from-my-grandmother"/>
    <updated>2015-05-04T12:00:00+00:00</updated>
    <id>http://hr2rh.com/three-lessons-hr-can-learn-from-my-grandmother</id>
    <author>
      <name>Resourceful Humans</name>
      <uri>http://hr2rh.com/</uri>
      <email>info@resourceful-humans.com</email>
    </author>
    <content type="html">
      &lt;img src=&quot;http://hr2rh.com/images/Omi2.001.jpg&quot;&gt;&lt;br/&gt;
      &lt;p&gt;My grandmother was a kick-ass lady. She raised six (!) children through a world-war. A war when she leaned in (without your book or a choice Sheryl). A war during which she and her children were denied access to the air raid shelters, because she was openly unsupportive of the Nazis. Instead of a karma reward, she lost my grandfather to a stroke way too early in her life, but just kept on trucking. “I’m sorry for you kids these days, you have it so much harder. I never had time for a depression, there was simply too much to do”, was all she had to say about all that… If you aren’t impressed yet, she had another superpower. She united a seriously dysfunctional clan of a family. Think Game of Thrones mixed with Pretty Little Liars. Yet everybody respected her because she listened to all members of her family on equal terms, never judged and was always open to talk. Always. That’s not a mean feat in such a big and complicated family full of egos. Yes, she had clear views on topics, but she did not try to make them yours. She simply united warring parties at one table in kitchen the size of your broom closet, served them a killer dish of home-made potato dumplings and pork chops until it felt like family again. The other day Pepper and I made the very same dumplings with our kids and I had to think of the valuable lessons I had learned from my “Omi”. Lessons that influenced me not just as a man, partner and father, but as an entrepreneur and as the notorious killer of HR.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Listen up HR peeps, here comes Granny:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;omi-was-the-center-not-the-top-of-the-family&quot;&gt;Omi was the center, not the top of the family.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;You have enemies? Great! That means you stood for something.
– Churchill&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Look at our organisational charts. They are still either functional or hierarchical. They go from top to bottom. They have no center. Not natural nor artificial. Simply none.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Omi was the center of the family as clearly as the planets revolve around the sun. My grandmother’s foremost quality was her smile framed by piercing blue eyes and an unrelentless positive attitude. I guess the latter being a side-effect of having survived the third Reich. It was this positive warmth that kept people in her orbit by choice. Don’t get me wrong, she wasn’t above dishing out a spanking. Actually, if you knew my aunt and uncles you would wonder why she wasn’t in spanking mode 24/7. How little she had to revert to authority and rules only serves to demonstrate her greatness. Her power was implicit. She believed in all of her flock, all evidence to the contrary. She embraced and accepted into her fold the likes of my dad, because she trusted her children’s judgement. She cared and provided for her rat pack in a way that engendered undying loyalty. The kind that had her kids come visit her not because they felt obliged, but because they loved to see her. Loved to talk with her. If not wiser, you always walked away more positiv from meeting my Grandmother.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Now bear with me and try to translate this to HR. A group of people whose positive power is so pervasive in an enterprise, people voluntarily seek their feedback and guidance. A group of people who make sure that there are as few rules and as many positive relationships as possible. A group of people who champion liberty and responsible maturity out of experiencing the opposite, enabling these qualities for others not because of elitist philosophy but experience that it is the best remedy to tyranny and hardship.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that sound about as far away as possible from the HR function you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There is something essential in the lesson I learned from my Grandmother that has influenced ‘The Way’ to democratic Entrepreneurship. The notion of mortality. When you love those around you and you accept that your time is limited, you act in a different way. I wish anyone who doubts our approach to ‘Kill HR’ would have been present at my Grandmother’s funeral. It was a small, private affair (as small as possible anyway with the closest German equivalent to small Arab family gathering). I vividly remember the words of the priest’s eulogy recounting that when he last spoke with her she told him she was ‘full of live’. Set this into the context of a German pun. “Satt sein”, “being full” can mean “being fed up”, as much as “being well fed”. My grandmother meant to say she was “well fed” with live. She had seen her children establish lives more safe and prosperous than her own. She had said farewell to loved ones and welcomed many grandchildren. Her life’s purpose truly was fulfilled. It was ok to go gently into that good night. As we stood in the little chapel, it would have become clear to anyone that the qualities of my grandmother were alive and kicking amongst all attendees. If the vessel was gone, the message remained. If anything her departure had re-enforced everyone’s commitment to them.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;What we call ‘the Obi-Wan’ effect in the context of ‘The Way’s’ management had its birth in this very intimate moment. The best HR is the one not needed. When we embrace HR’s role as such a mortal one and see it as an opportunity to inspire a legacy, we change our mindset. The same is true for the concept of management in service of self-governing teams, by the way. When we approach HR and Management not as a function (person), but as a set of behaviours (enabled and lived values), we act differently. When we are clear on what we stand for, what we stand against and who we stand with, our role becomes implicitly clear. Maybe our position is argued over, disagreed with or embraced – but clear. But it takes guts! Guts to go to a Managing Director and establish that clarity. Nothing great ever came without a fight. It takes guts and endurance to convince a rat-pack organisation that you are serious and won’t be swayed in your way. Just like refusing to seek shelter during an air-raid because you stand up for the right thing.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Does that sound like any HR function or Manager you know?&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson learned?  Become the center by leaving the circle. We need to understand that just like a great mother lives and acts independently to raise her kids  to live and act independently, HR needs to do likewise. If the organisation shall be more safe and prosperous as a legacy, we need to embrace our mortality as HR. Get a business canvas: put “100% Self-Government” down as core purpose of your being. Fill in the blanks. Now go get yourself some undying loyalties and enemies. Stand up for something. Live it. Compromise on the how, never on the what.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;omi-valued-action-over-words&quot;&gt;Omi valued action over words.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Be the change that you wish to see in the world!
-Gandhi&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;To call my love life turbulent is like saying the Hulk has minor anger management issues. In total desperation for game-changing life advise I turned to my Grandmother. I laid out to her exactly what had been said by whom when and expected a verdict from the mighty Oracle. My Grandmother’s feedback: ‘You think too much about what is said.You should pay more attention to what’s being done. As a matter of fact, forget what anyone is saying. Just watch what they are doing.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;There you have it. A lot of things suddenly made sense…&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;And hey – there’s a simple transfer to be made here to organisational ecology. I really wish I had a € for every-time an organisation knowingly tramples on the very values it espouses on the Culture/Recruiting part of its website.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample Problem: ’This manager repeatedly yells at his team-members and some people are already looking for other jobs.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Sample Excuse. uhmmm…we have no successors, and he gets the numbers. Give him another chance. People don’t leave so quickly in this economic climate.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People forget that Glassdoor and Kununu exist for a reason and that the worst precedent you let slip, sets the bar for your culture. No one out there says: they are a great company who hold their leaders accountable to their behaviour, it says so on their website. Those 15 negative reviews on Glassdoor are a fluke.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Above I said that organisational charts have no center. Not natural nor artificial. Simply none. That’s only half the truth. Organisations have values. Embodied in behaviour they create the unique culture. Usually there are values written down, but those aren’t the ones I mean. I mean the ones the organisation really lives. In the above example that value would be: ‘We let ourselves be blackmailed by Divas, because we are too chick-shit to risk a hit in performance to put our money where our mouth is.’ Some companies explicitly evoke the ‘No asshole’ Rule for such cases. No asshole is worth compromising what could be a great team.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;People forget that watching what organisations do is so much easier these days in a networked world. We don’t have to listen to what they say and take them on their words anymore. If HR is to become the bearer of the new world of work, we must do the same. We must live it! Take the case of eBay. When the top-management already knew they’d bow to lunatic investors like Icahn and his money-grabbing schemes to split PayPal off from eBay, the internal communications and HR department was busy rolling out a big “Better together” campaign. Now, you cannot tell me that the VP of HR was so blind or sidelined in the board, that she had no clue of the things to come (at least that’s what I hope for Beth Axelrod). That means you take your people for idiots. And then you wonder why change initiatives are greeted with cynicism and there are abysmal engagement scores. Examples like this abound. People stop listening, they watch the actions.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The hardest part when we partner with people to fundamentally change the game is to overcome years of cynicism, broken promises and internal propaganda – words. How do we do that? Action. It speaks so much louder than words. Say nothing. Just do something. People will make that action go viral soon enough, trust me. A CEO who gives up his office to sit with his team? One Tweet, a thousand retweets. A Manager who fires a known superstar bully in her team. That lady gains respect and emotional capital, because people build up trust again! The team will return that courageous move in improved performance 9 times out of 10.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Our awesome advisor Dan Walker, the former Chief Talent Officer at Apple during the Steve Jobs era nailed it. He told us a story where he sat in a C-level meeting with his peers and told them the performance reviews at Apple were abolished. They added no value, stole people’s time and served no purpose. His peers were shocked. This was an established ritual. What would take its place? Nothing, he answered. Nothing is better than to continue non-sense. But he was open to any better alternative that would espouse the Apple commitment to integrated Design and enable creating insanely great product. There were none. The performance reviews were gone. Well, hold on. Not quite. Before they were gone, the C-Level raised a stink of course. To which Dan answered: Would you like me to call Steve? Because this is aligned with him 100%.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Then they were gone. HR had drawn a line in the sand. Its actions (or its stand against non-sensical actions) spoke louder than a revamp, an iteration or a new brochure on performance management. It simply freed up time to actually perform.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson learned? Be critical what actions you take versus the words that you speak. As HR that means a whole lot. We ARE the custodians of culture. So, take stock, be honest with yourself. If you don’t know. Go out, wander around the organisation and ask people. Especially people you don’t know and who have no business kissing your ass. To effect meaningful change, you have to assess where you stand with words vs. action and then start taking decisive and consistent action! If not anywhere else do it internally. Get commitment: Let your crew vote for you as a leader. Free up time. Abolish performance management in your team. Demonstrate honesty: Make your salary transparent. Demand responsible action: Let your people take as many holidays as they like and work whenever wherever. Be an entrepreneur: Insist everybody draw up their on ‘Business Model You’ Canvas to demonstrate their contribution to the Customer. Be the future of work: Don’t order, create choices. Treat your team like partners and make all work contributions voluntary!&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Be the change you wish to see in the world. My Grandmother understood that.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;(…and my love life totally benefited from it :-)&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;h2 id=&quot;omi-was-practical-and-helpful&quot;&gt;Omi was practical and helpful.&lt;/h2&gt;

&lt;blockquote&gt;
  &lt;p&gt;Everybody has a plan until you get punched in the face.
– Mike Tyson&lt;/p&gt;
&lt;/blockquote&gt;

&lt;p&gt;When I had my first child, a wonderful daughter – I was as freaked out as the next father. 25 and burdened with the responsibility for a new life. AAAHHHHHHH!!!! I was out of my depth and felt the weight of the world on my shoulders. So I turned to my Grandmother – remember, mother of 7 – and asked her what I absolutely need to be aware of as a newly minted father. Omi thought for a moment – during which I totally expected trumpets and a choir, while I received gnosis – then said: ‘Keep the diapers at arms length on the baby’s changing table.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;The trumpets crashed, the choir died.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Wha….&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;‘I have heard of so many babies falling off the changing tables and their heads are still so delicate. Just make sure you can always have one hand on the baby so she does not roll off. The move quite quickly, you know.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;I was stunned. This was totally not the kind of ground-breaking parenthood advise I had wished for. Fortunately it was exactly the advise I needed. It wasn’t a theoretical paper on playground behaviour, or moving from authority to partnership parenting. It wasn’t a lecture on bi-lingual speech development or anything of the sort – it was sound practical advise. As simple as it was timeless and applicable.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;A similar thing happened to me when I spoke with our wonderful advisor Clovis da Silva Bojikian, the Guru of RH of Ricardo Semler’s SEMCO Group – the world’s first truly democratic company. When he visited us in Berlin to help usher in the next step for our company, I asked him what it took to create large scale organisational democracy like SEMCO. I mean, we’d done it for companies between 100 and 600, but he had succeeded to scale it to 8000 people! Which basically means you cracked the code and you might as well do it for 800.000. So, expecting his answer my trumpets hesitantly began playing, the choir began a careful crescendo, when Clovis said: ‘You will do the right thing, Heiko. I believe in you and your team.’&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;My trumpet players quit their job permanently and the choir now works for the Boston Consulting Group.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;He went on to tell me that it takes time to go your own way and that the worst I could do would be to try and copy SEMCO. The found their answers in their context in a time before Internet, before even Brazil was a democracy. Those answers would mean nothing to us. They had begun handing over responsibility to workers for the cafeteria food they complained about, for the colour of their overalls. What, Clovis asked, should I advise you? To make the lunch menu democratic? Maybe the food isn’t an issue so much outside Brazil. Maybe the overalls are regulated by some ISO norm in Europe. Who knows… But he did break it down to three simple rules he had followed:&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;ol&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Create choices&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Be transparent&lt;/li&gt;
  &lt;li&gt;Keep it small&lt;/li&gt;
&lt;/ol&gt;

&lt;p&gt;In our apple Juice and tomato juice analogy (for a different blog entry) this means that at different times in your organisational development, these three design elements can mean vastly different things. Just like giving choices was different for my Grandma with a 3 year old, a 9 year old and a 16 year old. As a new father the advise to keep the diapers at arm’s length ensured the health of my daughter so I could plan her Stanford application, so she could be the first woman on Mars. But I digress. I understood then, that people like my Grandmother, my parents and Clovis understood the underpinnings of these design principles and offered guidance and practical methods in the early stages of development, whereas they would move to increasingly abstract  coaching – sometimes flat out refusing advise – to engender seeking purpose, learning autonomy and developing mastery by myself. That phase might not be much appreciated, which is why it so important for HR to have a clear mission. The mission – the purpose – keeps you on track, not the popularity. Tough missions do not make for popularity contests, but if we cannot grow up to work with purpose, autonomy and mastery within HR, we have no credibility, no business and no experiential grounds to bring it to the teams around us. What my Grandmother, my parents and Clovis taught me was the MVP of life – going for iterating on a minimum viable product, until it stands on its own two feet as a mature responsible, independent adult. That’s mission accomplished.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;Lesson learned? Stop making grand plans. Forget the strategic recruitment plan. Forget the immense and useless competency portfolio, forget all the theoretical crap you spend most of your time with. Have a baby (just try something, create mvp products). Keep the diapers at arms length (know the business value creation chain, the exact numbers and how your product can solve issues or add value). Plan your value adding time between the diaper changes (fire fighting and recruiting usually) Change the diapers regularly (find a way to stay informed about the numbers and the non-numerical information by practise Management-By-Walking-Around). Hold hands for the first steps (launch the products in your own team, then with close support and training wheels in the teams around you). Create increasingly more open choices, be increasingly transparent about the how, why and what. Keep it small, family is everything. Have fun. Laugh a lot. Everybody has grand plans before the baby rolls off the changing table.&lt;/p&gt;

&lt;p&gt;That’s what my Grandmother taught me.&lt;/p&gt;


    </content>
  </entry>
  
  
</feed>